Harriot F. Curtis Papers, 1836-1963
Sophia Smith Collection
Harriot F. Curtis papers
1836-1963
1936-1963
Curtis, Harriot F.
MS 692
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Mill worker; Author. Curtis' writings and correspondence, historical research notes and background sources compiled during the 1950s and 1960s by biographer, Lila Wead Berman. 1840s publications about and from New England's mill workers included.
Harriot Flora Aurora Louisa Maria Curtis was born in Kelleyvale (now Lowell), Vermont on September 16, 1813, only a year after this Northeast Kingdom town incorporated, to Asahel (or Ashael) Jr. and Betsey Brigham Curtis. Her friend Harriet Hanson Robinson would later recall Curtis' unhappiness with her "lonely and isolated" existence in Kelleyvale. Like thousands of other young women in rural New England during the antebellum era, Curtis defied her parents and moved to Lowell, Massachusetts, to work in its burgeoning textile industry. She first appears on the Lawrence Manufacturing Company's payroll in 1833 as a harness knitter, considered one of the more skilled positions, staying through March 1838. Also a writer, the Lowell Casket, in which she had published, offered her an editorship position in 1837. In 1841 she began publishing in the corporate-sponsored literary magazine, Lowell Offering. Curtis became one of its two editors in 1842; responsible for soliciting subscriptions, she traveled widely. A year later, she and co-editor Harriet Farley bought the Lowell Offering, but the journal only lasted another two years and publication stopped in 1845. By then, Curtis had gained a measure of success after authoring the popular novel, Kate in Search of a Husband (1843), following it with the equally popular novel, Jessie's Flirtations (1846), and a collection of her wisdom, S.S.S. Philosophy (1847). Simultaneously, Curtis wrote for a number of newspapers including the Home Journal, the New York Tribune, the Lowell Journal, and the American of Lowell. During the 1830s and 40s, the open-minded Curtis maintained an interest in Swedenborgianism, threatened to join Shaker communes, and not only studied phrenology, but became a public lecturer on the topic and claimed eminent phrenologist O.S. Fowler as a mentor before disavowing the discipline by 1845. From 1854 to 1855, she served as editor of the Lowell weekly, Vox Populi. The antithesis of the Lowell Offering, the industry-critical Vox Populi spoke for workers rather than their employers. Curtis gave up her career after 1855, providing care to her ailing mother in Vermont. Curtis moved in with her sister Betsey's family in Needham, Massachusetts, upon her mother's 1859 death, living there for the remaining thirty years of her life. Writing in 1836 that "matrimony is an ocean upon which I shall not probably ever embark," Curtis never married, a lifestyle her friend and fellow former mill worker Harriet Hanson Robinson attributed to a shortage of suitable suitors. Writing in 2008 in the American Transcendental Quarterly, scholar Judith Ranta notes that "Curtis's fiction is striking for its critique of courtship and marriage, specifically the marriage market's oppressive effect upon young women." Styling herself a coquette, Curtis further reveals her critical ambivalence toward the institution of marriage in her lengthy correspondence with her suitor and friend, Hezekiah Morse Wead, whose proposals of marriage she rejected more than once.
The collection encompasses Curtis' writings and correspondence, as well as historical research notes and background sources compiled during the 1950s and 1960s by her aspiring biographer, Lila Wead Berman (great-granddaughter [?] of Hezekiah Morse Wead). The spirited and often flirtatious letters from Curtis to Hezekiah Morse Wead (1836-1845) have been fully transcribed and those typed transcriptions are also included in the collection.
While thirty-five letters and three full works from Curtis' own pen are represented, Lila Wead Berman's contextualizing sources and research notes comprise much of the collection, and include 1840s publications written by and about New England's mill operatives, an 1844 work of phrenology by Curtis' phrenological mentor, and twentieth century pamphlets on New England history and Swedenborgianism. Wead Berman's correspondence with various libraries and rare booksellers, bibliographies, a chronology of Curtis' life, and a paper she wrote critically examining Curtis' novel Jessie's Flirtations are contained in the papers.
This collection is organized into six series:
Biographical Material (1927-2012)
Correspondence (1836-1845)
Writings (1843-1847)
Subject Files (1844-1997)
Oversize Materials
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Sophia Smith Collection acquired the Harriot Curtis Papers from Maria Deforest McLeish, daughter of Lila Wead Berman, in 2012.
Authors, American -- 19th century -- Biography -- Sources; Authors, American -- Correspondence; Women workers -- United States -- 19th Century; Phrenology -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Swedenborgians -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Curtis, Harriot F.; Fowler, O. S. (Orson Squire), 1809-1887; Swedenborg, Emanuel, 1688-1772; Wead, Hezekiah M. (Hezekiah Morse), 1810-1876; Berman, Lila Wead; Berman, Lila Wead
- SERIES I. Biographical Materials (1927-2012)
  This series contains writings laying forth the history of the Wead family's associations with Harriot Curtis' story, and various plans to present it to the public. Also found in this series is Lila Wead Berman's chronology of Curtis' life, told largely through excerpts from Curtis' letters.
- SERIES II. Correspondence (1836-1845)
  This series consists of thirty-five letters Curtis wrote to her suitor, Hezekiah Mead Worse, as well as an inventory and typed transcriptions of each.
- SERIES III. Writings (1843-1947)
  Divided into two subseries, writings by Curtis, and writings from others, this series encompasses Curtis' novels Kate in Search of a Husband (1843), Jessie's Flirtations (1846), and her 1847 volume of wisdom, S.S.S. Philosophy, as well as Lila Wead Berman's research notes, bibliographies, and materials compiled to contextualize Curtis' life and times. Among the materials she collected are A.I. Cummings' 1847 novel The Factory Girl, as well as an 1841 Vindication of the Character and Condition of the Females Employed in the Lowell Mills, a May 1841 Lowell Operatives' Magazine, and Lowell's Lady's Pearl from March 1843.
- SERIES IV. Subject Files (1844-1997)
  The three subseries comprising this series are phrenology, Swedenborgianism, and New England history. The phrenology subseries contains an 1844 volume on the subject from Curtis' one-time mentor O.S. Fowler, as well as a 1997 article on phrenology. Lila Wead Berman's correspondence with distributors of Swedenborgian literature, as well as the pamphlets she acquired from them, dating between 1931-1958, make up the Swedenborgianism subseries. Wead Berman wrote to Boston's Old South Association in 1956 and acquired a number of their undated leaflets, which comprise the New England History subseries.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Wead Family's relationship with Curtis' story (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology of Harriot Curtis' life (Box 1, Folder 2)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Curtis' letters to Hezekiah Morse Wead 1836-45, [originals, please use transcripts] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lila Wead Berman's inventory and summary of Curtis' letters undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Transcripts of Curtis' letters to Hezekiah Morse Wead (Box 1, Folder 5-11)
  - Lila Wead Berman 1948-63 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lila Wead Berman and Margaret Storrs Grierson of the Sophia Smith Collection 1956-61 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Writings by Curtis, [see also box 2 for 2013 reprints]
    - Kate in Search of a Husband 1843 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Jessie's Flirtations 1846 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - S.S.S. Philosophy 1847 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings by others, [see also oversize materials]
    - Elisha Bartlett, M.D., A Vindication of the Character and Condition of the Females Employed in the Lowell Mills, Against the Charges Contained in the Boston Times, and the Boston Quarterly Review 1841 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The Operatives' Magazine, Containing Articles Upon Literary and Religious Subjects, Written By Manufacturing Operatives 1841 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Lady's Pearl; A Monthly Magazine, Devoted to Moral, Entertaining, and Instructive Literature 1843 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - A.I. Cummings, M.D., The Factory Girl: or Gardez La Coeur 1847 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Research notes on Curtis' character (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Lila Wead Berman, "An Instance of Counter-Sentimentalism in Popular Fiction of the Sentimental Period," unpublished paper 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - List of pieces published in the Lowell Offering undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Bibliography by Lila Wead Berman on the Lowell Offering and its contributors undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Research notes on Lowell Offering contributor Lucy Larcom undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Research notes on the Lowell Offering undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Research notes on Lowell and Curtis' era undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Research notes on Lowell undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES
  - Phrenology
    - Minna Morse, "Facing a Bumpy History: the Much Maligned Theory of Phrenology Gets a Tip of the Hat from Modern Neuroscience," Smithsonian Magazine (October 1997) (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - O.S. Fowler, A.B., Fowler's Practical Phrenology 1844 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Swedenborgianism
    - Correspondence of Lila Wead Berman and distributors of Swedenborgian literature 1956-60 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Pamphlets 1931-58, undated (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - New England history
    - Lila Wead Berman to the Old South Association 1956 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Old South Leaflets undated (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
- SERIES V. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Jessie's Flirtations 1846 (2013 reprint) (Box 2)
  - S.S.S. Philosophy 1847 (2013 reprint) (Box 2)
  - The Factory Girl's Garland, Exeter, New Hampshire 1844 (Map-case Flat file)